It is interesting that in the United States,
إنه من المثير للاهتمام أن في الولايات المتحدة
the most significant health-care budget
أهم ميزانية للرعاية الصحية
goes to cardiovascular disease care, whether it's private or public.
تذهب إلى رعاية الأمراض القلبية، سواء أكان خاص أو عام
There's no comparison at all.
ليس هناك مجال للمقارنة
In Africa -- where it is a major killer -- it is totally ignored.
في أفريقيا – حيث تشكل مرضا قاتلا – مغضوض النظر عنها تماما
And that situation cannot be right. We must do something about it.
و هذا الوضع لا يمكن أن يكون صحيحا. يجب أن نفعل شيئا من أجل ذلك
A health status of a nation parallels development of that nation.
الحالة الصحية لأمة توازي التطور لتلك الأمة
17 million people die every year from heart disease.
١٧ مليون شخص يموتون كل عام من مرض القلب
32 million heart attacks and strokes occur.
٣٢ مليون نوبة قلبية وسكتة دماغية تحدث.
Most of this is in developing countries, and the majority is in Africa.
أكثرها في البلدان النامية ، والأغلبية في أفريقيا.
85 percent of global disease burden for cardiovascular disease
٨٥ ٪ من عبء المرض العالمي لأمراض القلب
is in developing countries -- not in the West --
هو في البلاد النامية – و ليس في الغرب
and yet 90 percent of the resources are in the West.
و مع ذلك فإن ٩٠٪ من الموارد موجودة في الغرب
Who is at risk? People like you.
من في خطر؟ أشخاص مثلكم.
It's not just the Africans that should be concerned about that.
ليس فقط هم الأفريقيون الذين عليهم أن يقلقوا لهذا الأمر
All friends of Africa, that will have reason to be in Africa at some point in time,
جميع أصدقاء أفريقيا ، الذين سيكون لهم سبب للتواجد في أفريقيا في وقت ما
should be very concerned about this deplorable situation.
عليهم أن يكونوا قلقين لهذا الوضع المؤسف
Has anyone here wondered what will happen
هل من أحد هنا فكر في ما سيحصل
if you go back to your room at night,
إذا عدت إلى غرفتك ليلا
and you start getting chest pains, shortness of breath, sweating?
و بدأت تشعر بآلام صدرية، قصور في التنفس، و تعرق؟
You're having a heart attack. What are you going to do?
أصبت بنوبة قلبية. ماذا ستفعل؟
Will you fly back to the U.S., Germany, Europe?
هل ستغادر إلى الولايات المتحدة، ألمانيا أو أوروبا؟
No, you will die. 50 percent will die within 24 hours, if not treated.
لا، بل ستموت. ٥٠٪ يموتون خلال ٢٤ ساعة في حال عدم تلقي العلاج
This is what's going on.
هذا ما يحصل
In a look at the map of the U.S. -- the graph here,
عند النظر إلى خارطة الولايات المتحدة – البيان هذا
10 million people here, 10 million here.
١٠ ملايين شخص هنا، ١٠ ملايين هنا
By the time you get to 50, it's almost no one left in Nigeria --
بحلولك سن الخمسين، لن يكون قد تبقى أحد في نيجيريا
life expectancy is 47.
متوسط العمر المتوقع هو ٤٧
It's not because some people don't survive childhood illnesses --
ليس لأن بعض الأشخاص لا يتجاوزون أمراض الطفولة
they do -- but they do not survive after the time that they reach
إنهم يتجاوزونها – ولكنهم لا يعيشون بعد بلوغهم
about 45 years old and 50 years old.
سن ال٤٥ و سن ال ٥٠
And those are the times they're most productive.
و هذه هي الأوقات التي يكونون فيها الأكثر إنتاجا
Those are the times that they should be contributing
هذه هي الأوقات التي عليهم أن يقدموا فيها
to Africa's development. But they're not there.
لتطوير أفريقيا ، و لكنهم ليسوا هناك
The best way to spiral into a cycle of poverty is to kill the parents.
أفضل طريقة ليتحول الصراع من دائرة الفقر هو قتل الوالدين.
If you cannot secure the parents,
إذا لم تستطع تأمين الوالدين
you cannot guarantee the security of the African child.
لا تستطيع منح الأمن للطفل الأفريقي
What are the risk factors?
ما هي عوامل الخطر؟
It's very well known. I'm not going to spend a lot of time on those.
إنها معروفة جدا. لن أمضي الكثير من الوقت عليهم
These are just for information:
هؤلاء للمعلومية فقط:
hypertension, diabetes, obesity, lack of exercise. The usual suspects.
ارتفاع ضغط الدم وداء السكري والسمنة وعدم ممارسة الرياضة. المشتبه بهم عادة
Right here in Tanzania, 30 percent of individuals have hypertension.
هنا في تنزانيا، ٣٠٪ من الأفراد لديهم ارتفاع ضغط الدم
20 percent are getting treated.
٢٠٪ يتلقون العلاج
Only less than one percent are adequately treated.
أقل من ١٪ فقط تم علاجهم على نحو ملائم
If we can treat hypertension alone in Africa,
إذا تمكنا من علاج ارتفاع ضغط الدم في أفريقيا وحدها
we'll save 250,000 lives a year. That's quite significant!
سننقذ٢٥٠ألف حياة كل عام. هذا هام للغاية
Easy to treat. Look at the situation in Mauritius.
من السهل علاجه. انظروا الى الوضع في موريشيوس
In eight short years -- we're here talking about HIV, malaria,
خلال ٨ سنوات قصيرة – و هنا نتحدث عن الإيدز، الملاريا
which is all good.
و كله جيد
We cannot make the mistakes we've made with malaria and HIV.
لا يمكننا أن نفعل نفس الأخطاء التي فعلناها مع الملاريا والإيدز
In eight short years, non-communicable diseases
في ٨ سنوات قصيرة ، الأمراض غير المعدية
will become the leading causes of death in Africa.
سوف تصبح السبب الرئيسي للوفاة في أفريقيا
That is something to keep in mind. We can't deal with it with situations like this.
هذا شيء يجب أن يأخذ في عين الاعتبار. لا يمكننا التعامل مع مثل هذه الحالات
This is a typical African hospital. We can't depend on the elites --
هذا مستشفى أفريقي معتاد. لا يمكننا الاعتماد على النخبة --
they go to USA, Germany, U.K. for treatment. Unbelievable.
يذهبون إلى الولايات المتحدة، ألمانيا، وبريطانيا للعلاج. أمر لا يصدق
You can't depend on foreign aid alone.
لا يمكنك الإعتماد على المعونات الخارجية وحدها
Here is the situation: countries are turning inwards.
هذا هو الوضع: البلدان تنطوي إلى الداخل
Post-9/11, [the] United States has had a lot of trouble
ما بعد ١١ أيلول، أصبح لدى الولايات المتحدة الكثير من المتاعب
to deal with, their own internal issues.
للتعامل مع القضايا الداخلية الخاصة بها.
So, they spend their money trying to fix those problems.
لذلك ينفقون أموالهم في محاولة لحل هذه المشاكل
You can't rightly -- it's not their responsibility,
لا يمكنك بحق -- إنها ليست مسؤوليتهم ،
it is my responsibility. I have to take care of my own problems.
إنها مسؤوليتي. علي مراعاة مشاكلي
If they help, that's good! But that is not my expectation.
إذا قاموا بالمساعدة، فهذا جيد! و لكن هذا ليس توقعي
These worsening indices of health care or health studies in Africa
مؤشرات تدهور الرعاية الصحية أو الدراسات الصحية في افريقيا هذه
demand a new look. We cannot keep on doing things
تتطلب نظرة جديدة. لايمكننا الاستمرار في عمل الأشياء
the way we've always done them.
بالطريقة التي كنا دائما نفعلها
If they have not worked, we have to look for alternative solutions.
إذا لم تنفع، علينا أن نبحث عن حلول بديلة
I'm here to talk to you about solutions.
أنا هنا لأحدثكم عن الحلول
This has been -- what has been a difficult sign to some of us.
هذا ما كان علامة صعبة للبعض منا
Several years ago, we started thinking about it.
منذ عدة أعوام، بدأنا بالتفكير بها
Everyone knows the problem. No one knows what the solutions are.
الكل يعرف المشكلة. لا أحد يعرف ما هي الحلول
We decided that we needed to put our money where our mouth is.
قررنا أن ننفق المال في سبيل ما نؤمن به
Everyone is ready to throw in money,
الكل مستعد لدفع المال
in terms of free money aid to developing countries.
عبر معونات مجانية للدول النامية
Talk about sustainable investment, no one is interested.
عندما تتحدث عن الاستثمار المستدام لا أحد يهتم
You can't raise money.
فلا يمكنك جمع المال
I have done businesses in healthcare in the United States --
لقد قمت بأعمال في مجال الرعاية الصحية في الولايات المتحدة --
I live in Nashville, Tennessee, health care capital of America.
أسكن في ناشفيل، تينيسي، عاصمة الرعاية الصحية في أمريكا
[It's] very easy to raise money for health-care ventures.
من السهل جدا جمع المال لمشاريع الرعاية الصحية
But start telling them, you know,
و لكن قل لهم
we're going to try to do it in Nigeria -- everyone runs away.
سنحاول التنفيذ في نيجيريا – الكل يتهرب
That is totally wrong. Those of you in the audience here,
وهذا خاطئ تماما. منكم في الحضور هنا
if you want to help Africa, invest money in sustainable development.
إذا أردت مساعدة أفريقيا: استثمر المال في مشروع تنمية مستدامة.
Let me lead you through a day in the life of the Heart Institute,
دعوني أقودكم خلال يوم في حياة معهد القلب
so you get a glimpse of what we do,
لكي نلقي نظرة على ما نقوم به
and I'll talk a little bit more about it.
وسوف أتحدث قليلا عن ذلك.
What we have done is to show that high-quality health care,
ما قمنا به هو إظهار أن جودة الرعاية الصحية
comparable to the best anywhere in the world,
مقارنة بالأفضل في أي مكان في العالم
can be done in a developing country environment.
يمكن القيام بذلك في بيئة البلدان النامية
We have 25 positions right now -- all of them trained,
لدينا ٢٥ وظيفة في الوقت الراهن -- جميعهم من المدربين
board certified in the USA, Canada or Britain.
حاصلون على البورد في الولايات المتحدة، كندا أو بريطانيا
We have every modality that can be done in Vanderbilt,
لدينا كل طريقة يمكن أن يعمل بها في فاندربيلت
Cleveland Clinic -- everywhere in the U.S. --
عيادة كليفلاند – في كل مكان في الولايات المتحدة
and we do it for about 10 percent of the cost
ونحن نفعل ذلك بنحو ١٠٪ من التكلفة
that you will need to do those things in the United States.
المتطلبة لتفعل هذه الأشياء في الولايات المتحدة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Additionally, we have a policy
بالإضافة إلى ذلك ، لدينا سياسة
that no one is ever turned away because of ability to pay.
أن لا أحد يرد بسبب عدم القدرة على الدفع
We take care of everyone.
نرعى الجميع
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Whether you have one dollar, two dollars -- it doesn't matter.
سواء أكان معك دولار، دولارين –لا يهم
And I will tell you how we're able to do it.
و سأقول لكم كيف بإمكاننا عمل ذلك
We make sure that we select our equipment properly.
نتأكد من أننا نختار مُعداتنا بعناية فائقة
We go for modular units. Units that have multi-modality functions
نختار وحدات نموذجية. الوحدات التي لها وظائف متعددة
have modular components. Easy to repair, and because of that,
و عناصر معيارية. من السهل إصلاحها ، وبسبب ذلك ،
we do not take things that are not durable and cannot last.
لا نختار الأشياء الغير عملية و التي لا تدوم
We emphasize training,
نؤكد على التدريب
and we make sure that this process is regenerative.
نتأكد من أن هذه العملية قابلة على التجدد
Very soon we will all be dead and gone, but the problems will stay,
قريبا جدا كلنا سنموت و نرحل، و لكن المشاكل ستبقى
unless we have people taking over from where we stopped.
إلا إذا كان هناك أناس يستكملون بعد توقفنا
We made sure that we produced some things ourselves.
نتأكد من أننا قمنا أنفسنا بتصنيع بعض الأشياء
We do not buy unit doses of radiopharmaceuticals.
لا نشتري الجرعات الإشعاعية بالوحدات
We get the generators from the companies.
نحصل على المولدات من الشركات
We manufacture them in-house, ourselves. That keeps the costs down.
نصنعها على حسابنا الخاص. هذا يبقي التكاليف منخفضة
So, for a radiopharmaceutical in the U.S. --
فمثلا، المركبات الإشعاعية في الولايات المتحدة--
that you'll get a unit dose for 250 dollars --
يمكنك الحصول على وحدة جرعة ب ٢٥٠ دولار
when we're finished manufacturing it in-house,
عند الانتهاء من التصنيع على حسابنا
we come at a price of about two dollars.
أسعارنا تكون حوالي دولارين
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We recognize that the only way to bridge the gap
ندرك أن السبيل الوحيد للتقريب
between the rich and poor countries
بين الدول الغنية و الفقيرة
is through education and technology.
هي عن طريق التعليم و التكنولوجيا
All these problems we're talking about --
المشاكل التي نتحدث عنها --
if we bring development, they will all disappear.
إذاأحضرنا التطوير ، كلها ستختفي
Technology is a great equalizer. How do we make it work?
التكنولوجيا أداة لتحقيق المساواة . كيف يمكننا أن نوظفها؟
It's been proved: self-care is cost-effective.
لقد تم إثبات : الرعاية الذاتية فعالة من حيث التكلفة
It extends opportunity to the rural centers,
تمد الفرص إلى المراكز الريفية ،
and we can use expertise in a very smart way.
و يمكننا توظيف الخبرة بطريقة ذكية جدا
This is the way our centers are set up.
هذه هي الطريقة التي تقام بها مراكزنا
We currently have three locations in the Caribbean,
حاليا لدينا ثلاثة مواقع في الكاريبي
and we're planning a fourth one.
و نخطط للرابع
And we have now decided to go into Africa.
و الآن قررنا الذهاب إلى أفريقيا
We will be doing the West African Heart Institute
سننشأ مركز القلب الغرب أفريقي
in Port Harcourt, Nigeria. That project will be starting
في بورت هاركورت ، نيجيريا. هذا المشروع سوف يبدأ
within the next few months. We hope to open in 2008-09.
خلالالأشهر القليلة القادمة. نتأمل أن نفتتح في ٢٠٠٨-٢٠٠٩
And we will do other centers.
و سننشأ مراكز أخرى
This model can be adapted to every disease process.
هذا النموذج يمكن تعديله لكل مرض
All the units, all the centers, are linked
كل الوحدات، كل المراكز، متصلة
through a switched hub to a central server,
من خلال تحويلها الى مركز السنترال الخادم
and all the images are populated to review stations.
و جميع الصور تُجمع إلى محطات مراجعة
And we designed this telemedicine solution. It's proprietary to us,
و صممنا حل التطبيب عن بُعد. هذا ملكيتنا
and we are happy to share what we have learned with anyone
و نحن سعيدون بمشاركة ما تعلمناه مع أي أحد
who is interested in doing it. You can still be profitable.
من المهتمين. يمكنك أن تنتج أرباحا
We make sure that the telemedicine platform gives access
نتأكد من أن منصة التطبيب عن بعد تمنح الدخول
to expert medical specialists anywhere in the world,
للخبراء الأخصائيين الطبيين في أي مكان في العالم ،
just by a click of the button.
فقط بكبسة زر
I'll lead you through, to see how this happens.
سأقودكم خلال كيفية حصول هذا
This is at the Heart Institute. The doctors from anywhere can log in.
هذا في مركز القلب. الأطباء من أي مكان سيستطيعون الدخول
I can call you in Switzerland and say, "Listen, go into our system.
يمكنني أن أتصل بك في سويسرا و أقول، "اسمع، ادخل على نظامنا
Look at Mrs. Jones. Look at the study, tell me what you think."
انظرالسيدة جونز. انظر إلى هذه الدراسة، قل لي ما رأيك "
They'll give me that information,
يعطونني تلك المعلومات
and we'll make the care of the patient better.
و نجعل رعاية المريض أفضل
The patient doesn't have to travel.
لا يتوجب على المريض السفر
He doesn't have to experience the anxiety of not knowing
لا عليه أن يحس بالقلق الناشىء عن عدم المعرفة
because of limited expertise.
بسبب الخبرة المحدودة
We also use [an] electronic medical record system.
يمكننا أيضا استخدام نظام سجلات طبي الكتروني
I'm happy to say that the things we have implemented --
أنا سعيد بقول أن الأشياء التي قمنا بتنفيذها--
80 percent of U.S. practices do not have them, and yet the technology is there.
٨٠٪ من العيادات الأمريكية لا تملكها رغم وجود التكنولوجيا
But you know, they have that luxury.
و لكننا نعلم أنلديهم تلك الرفاهية
Because if you can't get it in Nashville, you can travel to Birmingham,
لأنه إذا لم تستطع الحصول عليها في ناشفل، يمكنك السفر إلى برمنجهام
two hours away, and you'll get it. If you can't get it in Cleveland,
على بعد ساعاتين، يمكنك الحصول عليها. إذا لم تستطع الحصول عليها في كليفلاند
you can go to Cincinnati. We don't have that luxury,
يمكنك الذهاب إلى سنسناتي. نحن لا نملك تلك الرفاهية
so we have to make it happen.
لذلك يجب علينا أن نجعل الأشياء تحصل
When we do it, we will put the cost of care down.
و عندما نجعلها تحصل، نخفض تكلفة الرعاية
And we'll extend it to the rural centers and make it affordable.
و نمدها إلى المراكز الريفية و تكلفتها معقولة
And everyone will get the care they deserve.
و الجميع سيحصل على الرعاية التي يستحقونها
It cannot just be technology, we recognize that.
لا يمكن أن تكون فقط تكنولوجيا، ندرك هذا
Prevention must be part of the solution -- we emphasize that.
الوقاية يجب أن تكون جزءا من الحل -- نؤكد على ذلك
But, you know, you have to tell people what can be done.
و لكن تعلم ، يجب أن تقول للناس ما يمكن فعله
It's not possible to tell people to do what is going to be expensive,
ليس من الممكن أن تقول لهم أن يفعلوا ما هو غال
and they go home and can't do it.
و يذهبوا للبيت ولا يستطيعون القيام به
They need to be alive, they need to feed.
عليهم أن يكونوا أحياء، عليهم أن يتغذوا
We recommend exercise as the most effective, simple, easy thing to do.
نُحبذ الرياضة كالأكثر فعالية، ببساطة و بسهولة
We have had walks every year -- every March, April.
نقوم بالمشي سوياً كل عام -- كل أذار و نيسان
We form people into groups and make them go into challenges.
نشكل مجموعات من الناس و نضعهم أمام تحديات
Which group loses the most weight, we give them prizes.
المجموعة التي تخسر أكثر وزن، نعطيها جوائز
Which groups record more walking distance by pedometer,
المجموعة التي تسجل المسافة الممشاة الأكثر بواسطة عداد الخطى،
we give them prizes. We do this constantly.
نعطيها جوائز. نفعل ذلك باستمرار
We encourage them to bring children.
نشجعهم على جلب الأطفال
That way we start exposing the children from very early on,
بهذه الطريقة نُعرض الأطفال من سن صغيرة
on what these issues are. Because once they learn it,
غلى ماهية هذه الأمور. لأن عند تعلمهم إياها
they will stay with it. In doing this we have created
سييقون عليها. من خلال فعل هذا كونا
at least 100 skilled jobs in Jamaica alone,
على الأقل ١٠٠ وظيفة ذات مهارات في جاميكا وحدها
and these are physicians with expertise and special training.
و هؤلاء هم الأطباء ذوي الخبرة و التدريب المختص
We have taken care of over 1,000 indigent patients that could have died,
لقد قمنا برعاية ما يزيد عن الألف مريض معوز الذين كان من الممكن أن يموتوا
including four free pacemakers in patients
بمافيها أربعة مرضى بضابط النبض
with complete heart block. For those that understand cardiology,
مع انسداد تام للقلب. و منكم من يفهم طب القلب
complete heart block means certain death.
انسداد القلب يعني الموت المحتم
If you don't get this pacemaker, you will be dead.
إذا لم تحصل على ضابط النبض هذا ، ستموت
So we are pleased with that.
فنحن سعيدون بذلك
Indirectly, we have saved the government of Jamaica five million dollars
بشكل غير مباشر، وفرنا ٥ ملايين دولار علٍى حكومة جاميكا
from people that would have gone to Miami or Atlanta for care.
من الأشخاص الذين كانوا سيذهبون إلى ميامي أو أطلنطا للرعاية
And we've hopefully saved a lot of lives.
و أنقذنا الكثير من الأشخاص
By the end of this year, we would have contributed over one million dollars
بنهاية هذا العام، سنكون قد قدمنا ما يزيد عن المليون دولار
in indigent care. In the first four months, it's been 340,000 dollars,
في رعاية المعوزين. في الأشهر الأربعة الأولى كان ٣٤٠،٠٠٠ دولار
averaging 85,000 dollars a month. The government will not do that,
بمتوسط ٨٥،٠٠٠ دولار شهريا. الحكومة لن تفعل ذلك ،
because they have competing needs.
لأن لديهم احتياجات متنافسة
They need to put resources elsewhere. But we can still do it.
عليهم أن يضعوا الموارد في أماكن أخرى. ولكن لا يزال بوسعنا أن نفعل ذلك.
People say, "How can you do that?" This is how we can do that.
لأن الناس تقول "كيف يمكنك فعل ذلك؟". هكذا نفعله
At least 4,000 rich Jamaicans that were heading to Miami for treatment
على الأقل ٤٠٠٠ جاميكي غني من المتجهين إلى ميامي للعلاج
have self-confessed that they did not go to Miami
اعترفوا ذاتيا بأنهم لم يذهبوا إلى ميامي،
because of the Heart Institute of the Caribbean.
بسبب مركز القلب الكاريبي
And, if they went to Miami, they will spend significantly more --
و إذا ذهبوا إلى ميامي سينفقون بشكل أكبر--
eight to 10 times more. And they feel happy spending it at home,
٨ إلى ١٠ أضعاف. و يشعرون بالسعادة عندما ينفقونها في بلدهم
getting the same quality of care.
و هم يتلقون نفس مستوى الرعاية
And for that money -- for every one patient that has the money to pay,
و لذلك المبلغ -- لكل مريض واحد عليه أن يدفع --
it gives us an opportunity to take care of at least four people
تمنحنا فرصة أن نرعى على الأقل ٤ أشخاص
that do not have the resources to pay.
لا يملكون الموارد الكافية للدفع
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
For this to work, this progress must be sustainable.
من أجل تحقيق هذا، يجب أن تكون العملية مستدامة
So, we emphasize training. Training is critical.
لذا نؤكد على التدريب. التدريب أمر بالغ الأهمية
We have gone further: we have formed a relationship
ذهبنا إلى أبعد من ذلك : لقد شكلنا علاقة
with the University of Technology, Jamaica,
مع جامعة التكنولوجيا، جاميكا
where I now have an appointment.
حيث تم الآن تعييني
And we are starting a biomedical engineering program,
وسنبدأ برنامج هندسة طبية حيوية
so that we will train people locally, who can repair that equipment.
حتى نتمكن من تدريب الناس محليا الذي يمكنهم تصليح تلك المعدات
That way we're not going to deal with obsolescence and all those kinds of issues.
وبهذه الطريقة لن نتعامل مع التقادم وجميع تلك الأنواع من المسائل
We're also starting ancillary health-care technology training programs --
سنقوم أيضا بابتداء برامج تدريب رعاية صحية تكنولوجية ثانوية --
training people in echocardiography, cardiac ultrasound,
تدريب الأشخاص في تخطيط صدى القلب، والموجات القلبية الفوق صوتية
those kinds of things. Now, with that kind of training,
هذا النوع من الأشياء. مع هذا النوع من التدريب
it gives people motivation.
تعطي الدافع للناس
Because now they will get a bachelors degree in medical imaging
لأن الآن سيحصلون على درجة البكالوريوس في التصوير الطبي
and all that kind of stuff. In the process, I want you to just hear
وجميع هذه الأشياء. خلال هذه العملية ، وأريدك أن تسمع
from the trainees themselves what it has meant for them.
من المتدربين أنفسهم ما يعني هذا بالنسبة لهم.
(Video) Dr. Jason Topping: My name is Jason Topping.
(فيديو) الدكتور جايسون توبنج : اسمي جيسون توبنج
I'm a senior resident in anesthesia in intensive care
أنا طبيب متدرب في التخدير في العناية المركزة
at the University Hospital of the West Indies.
في مستشفى لجامعة جزر الهند الغربية
I came to the Heart Institute in 2006,
جئت إلى معهد القلب في عام 2006
as part of my elective in my anesthesia and intensive care program.
كجزء من متطلباتي الاختيارية في التخدير والعناية المركزة
I spent three months at the Heart Institute.
أمضيت ثلاثة أشهر في معهد القلب.
There's been no doubt around my colleagues
لم يكن هناك شك بين زملائي
about the utility of the training I received here,
حول فائدة التدريب الذي تلقيته هنا،
and I think there's been an increased interest now in --
وأعتقد أن هناك اهتمام متزايد الآن --
particularly in echocardiography and its use in our setting.
خصوصا في التصوير القلبي الفوق صوتي
Sharon Lazarus: I am an echocardiographer at the Heart Institute of the Caribbean,
شارون لازاروس : أنا إيكوغرافية في معهد القلب من منطقة البحر الكاريبي
since the past two years. I received training at this institution.
منذ العامين الماضيين. تلقيت التدريب في هذا المركز
I think this aspect of training in cardiology
وأعتقد أن هذا الجانب من التدريب في مجال أمراض القلب
that the Heart Institute of the Caribbean has introduced in Jamaica
الذي بدأه معهد القلب من منطقة البحر الكاريبي في جامايكا
is very important in terms of diagnosing cardiac diseases.
مهم جدا بالنسبة لتشخيص أمراض القلب.
Ernest Madu: The lesson in this is that it can be done, and it can be sustained,
إرنست مادو : الدرس هنا أنه يمكن القيام به ويمكن أن يستمر
and you can make it possible for everyone.
و يمكنكم جعل ذلك ممكنا
Who are we to decide that poor people cannot get the best care?
من نحن لنقررأن هؤلاء الفقراء لا يمكنهم الحصول على أفضل رعاية؟
When have you been appointed to play God?
متى تم تعيينك لتمثل دور الإله
It is not my decision. My job is to make sure that every person,
إنه ليس قراري. مهمتي هي التأكد من أن كل شخص ،
no matter what fate has assigned to you, will have the opportunity
مهما كان المصير المحدد لك ، ستتاح الفرصة
to get the best quality health care in life.
للحصول على أجود رعاية صحية في الحياة
Next stop is West African Heart Institute,
المحطة التالية هي معهد القلب في غرب أفريقيا ،
that we are going to be doing in Port Harcourt, Nigeria,
التي سننشأها في بورت هاركورت ، نيجيريا
as I said before. We will do other centers across West Africa.
كما قلت سابقا، سننشأ مراكز اخرى في أنحاء غرب أفريقيا
We will extend the same system into other areas,
سنقوم بتمديد النظام نفسه إلى مناطق أخرى
like dialysis treatment.
مثل علاج غسيل الكلى
And anyone who is interested in doing it in any health care situation,
ولكل من يهمه الأمر للقيام به في أي حالة رعاية صحية
we will be happy to assist you and tell you how we've done it,
سنكون سعداء لمساعدتكم وسنقول لكم كيف فعلنا ذلك
and how you can do it. If we do this,
وكيف يمكنك أن تفعل ذلك. إذا كان لنا أن نفعل ذلك ،
we can change the face of health care in Africa.
يمكننا تغيير وضع الرعاية الصحية في أفريقيا.
Africa has been good to us; it is time for us to give back to Africa.
لقد عاملتنا أفريقيا جيدا؛ حان الوقت لنرد الجميل لأفريقيا
I am going. Those who want to come,
أنا ذاهب. ومن يريد أن يأتي،
I welcome you to come along with me.
أرحب بكم في مشاركتي
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)